Hello everyone, my
name is Noah Chernick,
I'm one of your academic
medicine scholars,
and I'm excited to
present to you guys about
the pathophysiology and
management of shock.
I'd like to thank Dr.
Yusupov, who helped me
create this lecture,
and let's get started.
Here are our learning
objectives for today.
So I wanted to quickly
describe the lecture
layout for you all. So
we're going to start
with the actual
measurements to describe
shock. These concepts
are also discussed in the
following lectures
that are listed below.
Here we're just going to
do a very brief overview
and introduce them in a
way that is applicable
to our discussion about
the pathophysiology.
After we go through
these measurements, we're
actually going to discuss
the four different
categories of shock,
and then finally we will
finish up with a little
bit of management
about how to deal with
the four types of shock.
So there are five
main measurements used
to determine what type
of shock a patient
is in. Hopefully you
guys have seen these
terms before in your
physiology lectures.
And again, just as a reminder,
we're not going
very in-depth here.
So one, post capillary
wedge pressure,
it's the measurement
of the pressure and
or volume of blood
in the left atrium.
Cardiac output is a formula,
which is essentially
the stroke volume and
the rate of the strokes.
Systemic vascular
resistance measures the
constriction of the
arterioles in the
systemic vasculature,
so essentially any form
of vessel that is
outside of the heart.
SVO2, or saturation
of venous O2, measures
the amount of oxygen in
the venous circulation,
so this actually will
assess the ability
of a tissue to extract
oxygen from the
arterioles and finally
central venous pressure
is essentially the amount
of blood returning to the
heart and think about this as
a counterpart to postcapillary
wedge pressure but this
measurement will assess
the amount of blood or
pressure in the right atrium so
for postcapillary wedge pressure
it is again the measurement
of the pressure in the
left atrium of the heart.
It is key for helping
to distinguish between
the two types of obstructive
shock, and we'll go
into these in a little
bit more detail later.
So if there's an
obstruction before the left
atrium, like a pulmonary
embolism or tension
pneumothorax, the
postcapillary wedge pressure
will be low. The blood
can't flow into the
left atrium from the
pulmonary vasculature.
If there's an obstruction
after the left atrium,
or there's obstruction
that affects the
entire heart, think of
something like a tamponade
where the entire heart
is squeezed down, the
post capillary wedge
pressure will be high.
And it can be measured
with a Swann-Gans catheter.
To review cardiac output,
again it's a formula derived
from the stroke volume
and rate. All changes in
cardiac output must be
produced by changes in either
one of these two things.
So you can either change
the heart rate or you can
change the stroke volume.
The cardiac output can be
altered by both sympathetic
and parasympathetic
responses, so that
essentially will increase
or decrease our heart rate.
And cardiac output
can also be altered by
the preload and
afterload in the left
ventricle, which affects
the stroke volume.
So total peripheral resistance
or systemic vascular
resistance, these two terms
can go interchangeably,
measures the overall level of
constriction in the
arterial system.
It's dictated by
the resistance of
the blood moving
through the arteries.
So if we look at this
formula here, there's
only a few things that
we can really change.
So R is the radius,
L is the length of
the vessel, and N is
the viscosity of blood.
It's a bit difficult to
change the length. You can
change the viscosity. Think
of someone with anemia,
may have a little bit less
viscous or thinner blood,
but radius has the largest
effect on total systemic
vascular resistance its
radius to the fourth power
so if we increase the radius
or vasodilate we're going
to drop the resistance in
the arterial system the
opposite is true as well
for if we constrict or make
the radius smaller so this
is going to be a really
important concept when we
consider the effects of
vasoconstriction and you'll
see this come into play a
little bit later in the
lecture saturation of venous
O2, or SVO2 for short,
measures the amount of oxygen
returning to the right
heart. It helps to assess
the amount of delivery of
oxygen and also the consumption
of oxygen in the tissues.
So if we have increased
SVO2, it actually represents
a decreased ability
of tissues to extract oxygen
from the blood. In the
opposite sense, if we have
a lower amount of SVO2,
it represents an
increased ability of
tissues to extract
oxygen from the blood.
So our last measurement,
central venous pressure,
shows or represents
the amount of volume
and pressure in the right
atrium of the heart.
Again, think about
it as the venous
counterpart of postcapillary
wedge pressure.
So central venous pressure is a
balance between two
opposing forces.
One is the ability of
the heart to pump blood
out of the right atrium
and ventricle and then move
into the lungs, and two,
the blood flow moving
from the peripheral veins
to the right atrium.
So we could think we'll
see an increase in central
venous pressure if we
have an increase in blood
volume, if there's an
increased large vessel tone, or
the most important, and
you'll see this with
distributive shock, is
dilation of the arterioles. So
essentially if we allow
more volume or more fluid to
move faster through the
circulation, you in theory
should see more fluid in
the central venous system.
So before we go
into the specific
categories of shock,
it's important to
understand what it
is as a general term.
So shock occurs whenever
there's a generalized and
severe reduction blood
supply to the body tissues
and the tissue needs are
not met, meaning the tissues
can't get enough oxygen
and nutrients to survive.
Even if we have
cardiovascular compensation,
arterial pressure
will still be low.
And shock is typically due
to one of two main themes
or physiologic concepts. So
you could have a disturbance
in cardiac output, so
the heart isn't working,
or maybe there's a blockage
somewhere in the cardiac
system, or systemic vascular
resistance has changed.
Adequate oxygen
therapy is reliant on
the following
physiologic parameters,
cardiac output and systemic
vascular resistance,
meaning again that the only
way to receive the amount
of oxygen necessary to
survive is through these two
parameters being almost in
sync. When we think about
vitals, especially blood
pressure, which is the main
measurement of shock,
think about shock if your
systolic is less than 90 or
your MAP is less than 65.
So here is a table of
four types of shock. It's
presented in this way for a
high-level overview. We're
going to go through each
of these four categories
and explain in much more
detail than this. As we
go through, you're going
to notice that there's
some measurement of one
of those five measures are
highlighted, and the
highlighted measurement is the
primary insult, meaning
that that is the main
driving cause of the type
of shock we're discussing.
So we have four types,
cardiogenic, distributive,
which is a vasodilatory
effect, hypovolemic, and
obstructive. You can read
the mechanisms, the examples,
and the primary insults
here, but we're going to
go into a lot more detail
in the following slides.
So our first type, hypovolemic
shock. The main cause
here is a loss of blood
or plasma volume, usually
around 20% of blood loss.
So some causes, it could
be a hemorrhage, so we're
just losing blood, or it
could be something where
we're severely dehydrated,
so severe vomiting or
diarrhea, it could be a heat
stroke, it could be severe
burns, or even think of
something like third spacing,
so if we don't have the proper
amount of colloids and
osmotic gradients in the
blood vessels, we could lose
fluid from an intravascular
space into an interstitial
space. So think about your
cirrhotic liver patients,
post-op, or pancreatitis.
for patient presentation
you're going to have narrow
pulse pressures very
important here cool and clammy
extremities that's because
there is a vasoconstrictive
effect you're going to have
poor capillary refill flat
jugular neck veins and a
dry mucous membranes overall
these individuals are
going to look like they're
fluid deprived and essentially
very very dehydrated so
looking at this from a
pathophysiologic perspective,
hypovolemia leads
to reduced cardiac
filling and reduced
stroke volume.
Preload in general
here is decreased.
So thinking about our
five measurements, central
venous pressure we
would see decreased or
lower value. This is
again because we have less
overall volume in
the body and in the
vasculature, so we'd
expect to see less overall
pressure and amount of
blood in the right atrium.
Postcapillary reg pressure,
which is the main or
primary insult is going
to be decreased. You're
going to have reduced overall
volume again which will
lead to a decreased amount
of blood in the left
atrium. You're going to
have a decreased preload.
For cardiac output it's
going to be decreased and
that's not because there's
a decrease in stroke
rate but more importantly
there's a reduced stroke
volume that reduces is your
overall cardiac output.
You'll actually have a
sympathetic reflex and have
an increase in stroke rate,
right? Your heart rate will
get faster if the
baroreceptors understand that
there's not enough pressure,
not enough fluid, so you'll
actually have a
reflexive tachycardia and
vasoconstriction, which actually
leads into our next point.
Systemic vascular
resistance is going to be
increased. You're going
to see an increased SVR
in almost all the types
of shock we discuss.
So the baroreceptors
will sense a decreased
mean arterial pressure
and will increase
vasoconstriction by
making the radius of
the vasculature,
especially the arterioles,
smaller.
And finally, SVO2 is
going to be decreased.
Because we have a higher
systemic vascular resistance,
the flow of blood is
actually going to be slower
in the capillaries.
Because the flow of blood
is slower, you're actually
going to have an increased
amount of time for gas
exchange in the tissues.
This may be a little
bit counterintuitive,
where if you'd expect
a higher resistance
that the blood can't
really make it to the
tissues, but it's
actually the opposite.
So again, just think
if the blood is moving
slower through the
capillaries, there's more
time for gas exchange
to happen where oxygen
can move from the
blood into the tissues.
Here's a small diagram
depicting hypovolemic shock.
Again, we're going to
see signs of tissue
hypoperfusion, meaning
the tissues aren't getting
enough nutrients to survive,
which then leads into
a circulatory and or
hypovolemic shock picture.
So low estimated
cardiac output and
SVO2, low central
venous pressures, and
you see a hypovolemic
circulatory shock.
So for cardiogenic
shock, the main cause
is decreased myocardial
contractility.
So think of things
like a heart attack,
cardiomyopathy because
of virus or a drug,
decompensated heart failure,
acute or end-stage valvular
disease, and also dysrhythmias.
For patient presentation,
again, you're going to have
narrow pulse pressures,
cool and clammy extremities,
a poor capillary refill,
and then these last four
presentation signs here.
So your elevated jugular
venous pressure, your
positive hepatojugular reflex,
an S3 gallop, and pulmonary
rails are all because
the heart is unable to
clear or pump the amount of
blood moving back through
the venous system. So
you're going to see a fluid
overloaded patient here.
So the pathophysiology
of cardiogenic
shock. Cardiac failure
leads to increased
preload and reduced
cardiac output.
So for central venous
pressure, we're going to
see an increased amount.
We have fluid accumulation
behind the heart. So
we're going to have more
fluid in the right heart
and the venous system.
Postcapillary reg pressure
is going to be increased.
Again, a similar concept
to central venous pressure.
Preload is increased, but
stroke volume is decreased.
We have fluid buildup
behind the heart. This time
we're talking about the
fluid in the left atrium.
Cardiac output, which
is our main insult or
primary insult, is
going to be decreased.
Reduced stroke volume will
reduce overall cardiac
output. We have a decreased
ejection fraction.
Essentially think about
this as the heart is
unable to pump enough
blood out of the heart to
satisfy the tissue
requirements.
Systemic vascular resistance
again is going to be increased.
Because we have a failing
heart, we're not going
to have an adequate MAP
or adequate pressure,
so the baroceptors will
sense this decreased
mean arterial pressure
and will have a reflexive
vasoconstriction.
SVO2 is going to be
decreased. This
is again a similar
concept with the
increased resistance.
Essentially expect
to see these two
go hand in hand. We
have an increased
SVR, you should see
a decreased SVO2.
So the high resistance
slows the flow of
blood through the
capillaries increasing
the amount of time
for a gas exchange.
Here's a diagram of
cardiogenic shock.
So obstructive shock, our
next type. There are actually
two different causes of
obstructive shock and
we're going to see slightly
different measurements
when we talk about our five
main measures for shock.
So the first type could
be a pulmonary obstructive
shock. So think about this
as some form of obstruction
in the pulmonary vasculature.
So you're going to
see an increased right
ventricular afterload, meaning
that it's harder for the
right ventricle to pump
blood into the pulmonary
system, but at the same time
you're going to see a
decreased left ventricle
preload, meaning that there's
not enough fluid moving
back from the lungs into
the left side of the heart.
There's an increased
resistance within the
pulmonary circulation
that prevents blood from
reaching the left side
of the heart. So here the
big one to think about
is pulmonary embolism.
The other type is a structural
or obstructive shock.
This is a decreased right
ventricle preload type of
situation so think about here
there's restricted diastole
or filling in general so
the big one here cardiac
tamponade you could also think
about constrictive pericarditis
anything that limits the
ability of the heart to
dilate and fill so for
obstructive shock again very
similar to the following three
narrow pulse pressures cool
and clammy extremities and
a poor capillary refill.
In a tension pneumothorax
situation, expect absent
breath sounds. For cardiac
tamponade, you could
think about distant heart
sounds, jugular venous
distension, and hypotension.
For pulmonary embolism,
think about dyspnea and
shortness of breath.
For pathophysiology,
again, obstruction leads
to a decreased preload
and a reduced cardiac
output. Again, very
similar concept to the
two previous ones we
were discussing, especially
cardiogenic shock.
So for central venous pressure,
again, we would expect
it to be increased. We
have more fluid behind the
heart in the venous system.
The heart isn't able to
pump it because of some
obstruction, so we're going
to have a backup in the
venous system. Your post
-capillary wedge pressure is
going to be variable here.
So for a pulmonary
obstruction, we have something
blocking the pulmonary
vasculature, the postcapillary
wedge pressure or the
measurement of pressure
in the left atrium is
going to be decreased. So
blood is obstructed before
we enter that left atrium.
We're going to have
decreased left ventricle
preload and an increased
right ventricle afterload.
If we have a cardiac
constriction, the postcapillary
wedge pressure is
going to be increased.
Think about this as
a cardiac tamponade.
So the entire heart
here is constricted.
we have reduced
diastolic filling ability
and decreased stroke
volume all together.
We're going to have a
decreased right ventricle
preload and a decreased
diastolic filling.
For cardiac output, regardless
of where the obstruction is,
the heart isn't able to pump
the right amount of blood
out into the system, so
we're going to have a
decreased cardiac output,
again because of stroke volume.
Systemic vascular
resistance is going to be
increased. Again, similar
concept. Because our
cardiac output is failing,
we have dropped arterial
pressures, central
nervous system will
promote vasoconstriction,
making the radius of those
vessels smaller,
increasing our resistance.
And again, these two go hand in
hand. SVO2 will
be decreased here.
Higher resistance means
the blood is moving
slower through the
capillaries, increasing
the amount of time
for gas exchange.
Here's a diagram of
obstructive shock. Again, we
could have two different
places where the obstruction
is occurring. It could
be in the actual heart
itself, so the heart
isn't able to fill, or
there could be an obstruction
between the right side
of the heart and the
lungs, meaning that blood
is not flowing into the
left side of the heart.
So the last type of
shock actually has three
different types within
it. So distributive shock.
The main cause here, the
main aspect that creates
distributive shock is a
loss of vascular tone.
So what I mean by that
is the vessels aren't
able to vasoconstrict
anymore. They very much
dilate, causing a severe
drop in blood pressure.
So there are three types,
two that we'll talk
about a little bit more,
and then one that we'll
just touch on just so
you have a complete idea,
but it's not as necessarily
heavily stressed.
So for septic
shock, anaphylactic
shock, and neurogenic
shock, the first
two are the main
ones we talk about.
Sepsis, again, is
due to infection, and
anaphylaxis is an
allergic reaction.
Neurogenic, we'll talk
about, it's usually
due to a nervous
system insult, so
a brain injury or a
spinal cord injury.
For patient presentation,
this is going to be a
very different kind of
presentation compared to the
previous three types of
shock so now we have a
wide pulse pressure we
also have warm and dry skin
compared to the cool and
clammy skin we talked
about with the three other
types of shock this is a
really important thing
to look on when we think
about practice questions
either for exams or boards
because warm and dry skin
should be an immediate
tell that this is a form
of distributive shock,
not your cardiogenic,
obstructive, or hypovolemic.
In neurogenic shock, you're
going to have loss of
sympathetic tone. And think
about with anaphylaxis,
you're going to see
some signs and symptoms.
So hives, uticaria,
stridor, airway compromise.
So again, for
pathophysiology, distributive
shock is due to
loss of vascular
tone, leading to
decreased resistance.
So our primary insult
here is a drop of
systemic resistance.
We have a vasodilatory
effect in the
systemic vasculature.
So for central venous
pressure, you may actually
expect this to be
increased, and I want to
talk a little bit about
if you are confused
about this. So for central
venous pressure, the
vascular tone is going
to be dropped in the
venous system as well
as the urcarial system.
So even though the blood
has less resistance to move
back into the heart, instead
of moving back into the
heart, the blood is going to
pool in the venous system.
So we're going to have
decreased amounts of blood
moving back into the right
atrium, increased amounts
still sitting in the
venous vasculature. So our
central venous pressure is
going to be decreased here.
Postcapillary wedge pressure
is going to be decreased.
We have increased
vasodilation, allowing for
more blood to remain within
the circulatory system.
Similar concept
that we just spoke
about with the central
venous pressure.
Cardiac output is actually
going to be variable here.
So for your septic and
anaphylactic shocks, you're
going to see an increased
cardiac output, and this is
because of the sympathetic
response to a drop of the
vascular cone. So again,
the baroceptors are going to
realize that there is drop
in pressure and cause a
reflexive tachycardia. In
neurogenic it's going to be
decreased and this is because
there's no sympathetic
response due to an injury of
the central nervous system.
So the baroreceptors will
still notice that there
is a drop in blood
pressure but the central
nervous system does not
have the ability to cause a
reflexive tachycardia
because there's some form
of injury with the
signaling back to the heart.
Your systemic vascular
resistance is decreased.
Again, this is driving all
the physiologic changes
and the disturbance we
see in distributive shock.
SVO2 here is actually now
going to be increased.
Because we have a lower
amount of resistance in
the capillaries, we have
an increased speed of
the blood moving through
the capillaries. Since the
blood is not sitting in
the capillaries as long
as you would see in the
other three types of
shock, you're actually
going to have an increased
SVO2 because there's less
time for gas exchange.
So here is a diagram
of distributive
shock. Again, one of
the main signs that we
could think about
here is warm and dry.
So for the pathophysiology,
for septic shock, again
we're not going to go into as
much details our microbiology
courses. This is more
of a high-level view and
why we see septic shock
causing vasodilation. So septic
shock is usually caused
by gram-negative bacteria
mediated by endotoxins known
as lipopolysaccharides.
Within the LPS, specifically
on the lipid A portion,
it binds to pattern
recognition receptors called
toll-like receptor 4 on
macrophages and B cells.
Activating toll-like
receptor 4 stimulates the
production of IL-1, TNF,
and IL-6. These cytokines
promote fever, weaken the
bond between endothelial
cells, and recruit further
inflammation in the cells.
Nitric oxide is also released,
causing vasodilation.
So very briefly, to kind
of recap these two things,
we're going to have an
increase of vascular radius,
right, with our vasodilation
due to nitric oxide,
but also when we weaken the
bond between endothelial
cells, it allows for some
of the fluid within the
vasculature to escape into
an interstitium. So this
is what we were talking
about a little bit earlier
as something you can see
in the hypovolemic patient
with third spacing. You
also see it in septic shock.
LPS can also activate
the coagulation cascade,
which causes disseminated
intravascular
coagulation via tissue
factor production.
You don't, for our
purposes, need to understand
that whole entire pathway,
just more recognize
it as a potential
result of septic shock.
So there are a few
criteria that help
define or identify
sepsis in patients.
The first one is SERS
criteria. It's a little
bit older and it's
typically you see used
a little bit more in
a hospital setting to
assess systemic
inflammation and or sepsis.
SERS is defined of meeting
two of the four following
criteria. So a temperature
over 38 or under 36,
heart rate greater than
90, your respiratory rate
greater than 20 breaths
per minute, or a partial
pressure of CO2 less than
32 millimeters of mercury,
and your luteocyte
count is greater than
12,000 or less than
4,000, or over 10
% immature bands of
white blood cells.
As you can see here, this
criteria is a little bit loose.
There's a bunch of different
things that can cause
all of these responses,
right? You could have an
individual who may just be
a little short of breath.
You could see them at
tachycardic and a respiratory
rate greater than 20.
That doesn't necessarily
mean they have systemic
inflammation and or sepsis.
So for some definitions,
sepsis is a life
-threatening organ dysfunction
caused by dysregulated
host response to
infection. Severe sepsis
is sepsis with one or
more end-organ failures.
septic shock is then
when we see a hemodynamic
instability despite intravascular
volume repletion what
i mean by that is that we're
trying to replete fluids
either through blood or
saline or some form of
iv fluid and they're still
hemodynamically unstable
so septic shock can also
be defined as sepsis and
a vasopressor therapy needed
to elevate the MAP over
65, and if you have a
lactate reading of over 2.
So another indication
or measurement
system for sepsis
is QSOFA and NEWS.
The first one SOFA or
sequential sepsis related
organ failure assessment
is defined of meeting two
of the three criteria,
respiratory rate greater
than 22 per minute, altered
mentation so altered
mental status, and a
systolic BP less than 100.
SOFA in general thinks
about helping to warm
clinicians to further
investigate organ dysfunction.
There's also NEWS or
National Early Warning
Score based on point
system of the following
physiologic parameters,
so your respiratory
rate, oxygen
saturation, systolic BP,
pulse level of consciousness
or confusion, and temperature.
And you have different
criteria based off of how
many points. And just very
briefly we talk about these
kind of systems to identify
sepsis not for you guys
to memorize it and spend
time thinking about oh well
is this one point or two
points it's more to help you
understand that what should
a patient look like when
i'm thinking sepsis and
these systems will be used on
your rotations you may hear
sirs or you may hear q sofa
so again just wanted to
introduce them now so you
may be aware and when you
need to more have a greater
grasp of them in terms of
values and points on a third
year rotation you already
have kind of the background
so for treatment we want to
start obviously with broad
spectrum antibiotics until
we get blood cultures back
so the goal here initiate
iv antibiotic therapy within
the first hour after
diagnosis of sepsis or septic
shock your big hitter
antibiotics here your super broad
spectrum so your vancomycin
and cefepime or piperacillin
depending on the hospital
setting for the hypotension
you typically start with
iv fluid repletion usually
a crystalloid solution and
we'll discuss crystalloid
versus colloids in the upcoming
slides if we cannot get
the blood pressure elevated
enough with just fluids
we then need to move into
our pharmacologic therapies.
So think about our vasopressors.
The key for sepsis,
the key for curing and
fighting off sepsis before
it creates a more systemic
effect is identifying
the source of infection
and removing it if it's
some form of foreign body
or kind of cyst or abscess
and that greatly increases
the rate of success.
From the picture on here, the
surviving sepsis campaign,
there's a one-on-hour
bundle for the initial
resuscitation, so we want to
measure lactate levels, we
want to get our blood
cultures before administering
antibiotics, that way that
we don't kind of skew any
result. You administer your
broad spectrum while you
await results, and then you
begin with rapid administration
of about 30 milliliters
per kilogram of a fluid.
And then if all else
fails, you start
moving into
vasopressor territory.
For anaphylactic shock,
similar idea, a little
bit different presentation
obviously than a septic shock.
So anaphylaxis is an allergic
condition where arterial
pressure decreases drastically.
It's caused by an antigen
antibody reaction, and
this reaction causes a cascade
of effects resulting in
mast cells in the periphery
and basal cells in the
blood to release histamine
or histamine-like substances.
Histamine and the
histamine-like substances
increase vascular capacity
and venous dilation.
We're going to see an
increase in dilation of the
arterioles, increased
capillary permeability with
loss of fluid and protein
into the tissue spaces.
From a physiologic presentation
in terms of our five
measurements, absolutely
identical to septic shock. If
you were given a table with
our five measurements and
you were asked, is this
septic or anaphylactic shock,
you'd have a really, really
hard time understanding or
determining which one it
is. However, obviously our
physical presentation is going
to be a little bit different.
For anaphylaxis, think about
throat swelling, coughing
and wheezing, vomiting,
diarrhea, abdominal pain,
hives, tachycardia, uticaria,
and also tongue
swelling or lethargy.
For treatment, most important
treatment in anaphylaxis
is epinephrine in an
intramuscular application.
You can think about
additional treatments as
well, so normal saline to
treat hypotension, oxygen,
and albuterol, which helps
decrease bronchospasm,
especially if present still
after the epinephrine.
So in neurogenic
shock, we want to think
about dysregulation
of autonomic nervous
system causing a lack
of sympathetic tone
and unopposed
parasympathetic response.
Our causes here include
deep general anesthesia,
spinal anesthesia,
or brain damage. All
these causes in general
you can think about
as no longer being able
to deliver a sympathetic
response to the heart
and vasculature.
Presents very
similarly to septic and
anaphylactic shock, except
there's no tachycardia
because we can't
have that reflexive
tachycardia due to
no sympathetic tone.
So here's a table of
the results of shock. I
want to talk a little
bit about how to kind of
study and learn about
the four types of shock.
So you can just
memorize this table
and understand where
the primary insult
is and what's up
and what's down.
But you're not
necessarily learning
about shock, you're
memorizing a table.
As you move through
your second year
and start moving
into boards, which
will come up sooner
than you realize,
there's a lot of information
that you need to memorize.
Shock is one of those
things that you can
actually rationalize
your way through.
If you understand the
underlying mechanisms and
the physiology of each of
these five measurements,
you don't ever have to
actually memorize a table.
You can rationalize
through your head with,
for example, a hypovolemic
shock. I'd expect
increased SVR because
we have decreased blood
pressure and a
decreased postcapillary
wedge pressure because
we have a drop preload.
So take this with a grain
of salt if for you you
just have to memorize this
because of whatever reason
go for it but I encourage
you guys to spend a
little bit more time right
now learning it in terms
of theories and something
you can rationalize and
work through and it will
help you in the long run.
So going back to our table,
we have our types of shocks
and our examples of causes.
We spoke about almost
all of these and just generally
the decreases or increases
in our five measurements
here. One thing I do want
to point out is with our
distributive shock, it is
the only one where we're
going to have a increase in in
SVO2 and a decrease in SVR,
right? So if you're seeing
an exam question and you
have a drop in systemic
vascular resistance and an
increase in SVO2, you don't
even need to think about the
three other types of shock.
At this point, you need to
be thinking about is this
septic, is this anaphylactic,
or is this neurogenic?
So for clinical presentation,
we spoke about general
presentation and signs and
symptoms with each type,
but I want to just kind of
group them together now. So
obviously hypotension is
going to be a big one. Shock,
by definition, is a drop
in systemic blood pressure.
So you can see tachycardia
or bradycardia,
depending on the type of shock,
depicnea, so increase
in respiratory rate,
altermentation, they could
be agitated, hypoxemia,
oliguria, or anuria.
You're going to see cool
extremities in anything
with an increase of systemic
vascular resistance,
so your hypovolemic,
cardiogenic, and
obstructive shocks. You're
going to actually have
warm and dry extremities
in septic shock where
we have a drop in systemic
vascular resistance.
You could have cyanosis,
blue pale or discolored
skin, and a slow capillary
refill. You could also
see peripheral edema due
to a third spacing effect.
So now we're going
to talk about our
management of shock.
So you could kind of
guess through discussing
the pathophysiology
what our management
strategies will be.
So for our cardiogenic shock,
our management is going
to be inotropes, so trying
to get the contractility
up, and further cardiac
intervention, but that's
well beyond the scope of
this lecture talking about
surgical or procedural
things that we can do for
cardiogenic shock. For
distributive shock or vasodilatory
shock, same thing. We're
going to have fluid
resuscitation. If they're
septic, we want to start them on
broad spectrum antibiotics.
And if they're an
anaphylactic, we're going
to give them intramuscular
epinephrine. For hypovolemic,
we're going to do fluid
resuscitation and pressors to
vasoconstruct even further.
And for obstructive,
same idea. We're going to
do fluid resuscitation,
and we're going to try to
relieve the obstruction if
possible. So if there's a
pulmonary embolism, we want
to try and remove it. If
there's a tamponade or
pericarditis, we want to try
and relieve some of the
pressure that's on the heart.
So to very briefly just
talk about types of blood
transfusions or blood
products that we can use,
we have packed red blood
cells. So think about
using this for a mass
transfusion protocol in
hemorrhagic shock. Fresh
frozen plasma, again consider
for a transfusion protocol.
You could also use
it to combat DIC, which
occurs with septic shock.
With platelets, you can
give it to treat bleeding
and cryoprecipitate for
fibrinogen repletion.
So used much more often
than blood products are
IV fluids, and they are
broken down generally
into two different
categories. So you have your
crystalloids, and those
are the types of fluids
that have smaller molecules.
So your bigger ones
that are commonly used
are 0.9% normal saline,
but the concern with that
is a potential metabolic
acidosis from hyperchloremia
in large fluid resuscitation.
You also have ringers
lactate solution that has
a lower chloride equivalent,
but it does come with its
own risks. There's real no
clear-cut better crystalloid
when we compare lactate
ringers to normal saline.
There is something called
plasmalite, which is a
balanced salt solution that
matches the electrolyte
content of the plasma almost
perfectly but it's a lot
more expensive than ringers
lactate and normal saline
so it's not used as much
colloids have larger molecules
that can't necessarily
escape the plasma so those
your proteins your dextrin
think of albumin generally
there are no differences
between patient outcomes
when we think about crystalloid
and colloid solutions.
So please don't feel
like you need to
memorize this entire
chart. This is
again just more for
visual learners.
So here's our human plasma
volumes. Again we talked about
for 0.9% saline or normal
saline we have a much
higher chlorine content
than in the plasma and for
ringers lactate we have
a much lower or a little
bit lower sodium compared
to our plasma volumes. So
that could actually cause
a metabolic alkalosis.
So when we want to think
about which fluid, think
about a blood transfusion
when you have a hemoglobin
below 7. For colloids, albumin
really doesn't have any
long-term benefits over
crystalloids and it may be
a little bit more expensive.
So typically your first
line option is going to be
a crystalloid substance.
And again there's no clear
-cut better crystalloid
when we compare lactate
ringers to normal
saline. For normal saline,
you do run the risk of
hyperchloremic metabolic
acidosis due to a higher
chloride quantity. And
for ringers lactate, it
is closer to physiologic
concentrations, but you
can run the risk of a
hyponatremia. In general,
when thinking about how
much to give a patient,
the surviving sepsis
campaign recommends at least
30 milliliters per kilogram
of crystalloids within
the first three hours.
So for an example, if you
have a 70 kilogram patient,
they should receive around
2100 milliliters or about
two liters of fluid.
And finally, how do we
want to assess fluid
levels? There are a
few different ways to
do it. You could do it
clinically, so looking
at the heart rate,
the blood pressure,
their urine output, asking
your patients if they're
able to respond to you,
what color is their urine,
skin turgor, so does the
skin tent when you pull it
up or does that snap
back, and finally do their
mucous membranes look dry.
For vitals as well, it could
be very beneficial to
look at the math and SVO2.
So for medications, we do
have a bunch of vasoactive
agents. I know you all
learned these during
the spring semester of last
year with Dr. Goldstein,
but we are going to
discuss them briefly again.
So while addressing the
underlying cause of shock
is the best treatment
modality, vasoactive
agents can help restore
blood pressure if needed.
So for septic shock,
norepinephrine
is our first-line agent.
Dobutamine or another
anotrope should be used for
cardiogenic shock, so think
about any type of situation
where we need to increase the
contractility of the heart,
we want to use an anotrope.
There are a lot of
complications and side effects
of our vasoactive agents.
So extravasation, so you
could have vasoconstriction
of nearby connective tissue
can cause skin necrosis.
If you see this, if you
have an ICU rotation,
you may see individuals
on pressors start to
kind of have skin necrosis
near the IV sites,
as well as on the
periphery you can see some
signs of skin death because
of the vasoconstriction.
You also have
hypoperfusion. So prolonged
vasoconstriction can produce
inadequate perfusion to
the extremities, mesenteric
organs, and kidneys.
So yes, you're treating
the vasodilation and you're
treating the shock with
these vasoactive agents.
But at the same time,
you're also causing
further harm because
you're hypoperfusing
some essential organs and
the extremities as well.
So here are our vasoactive
agents. I'm gonna
briefly go through each
one. So for norepinephrine,
we can have it for a
few different types
of shock, distributive,
cardiogenic, or mixed.
Primary mechanism is
alpha-1 agonism with a
little bit of beta
agonism as well. Our major
effects, we're going
to increase systemic
vascular resistance as
well as cardiac output.
And this is typically
a first choice presser.
There are some adverse
side effects of it,
tachyarrhythmias, you
could have ischemia.
For phenylephrine, again,
distributive and hypothalamic
shock, this is a pure alpha
-1 agonism, so think just
straight increases in
systemic vascular resistance.
For vasopressin,
again, distributive and
cardiogenic shock, this
is our V1, V2 receptor
binding, and similar to
phenylephrine, almost
strictly systemic vascular
resistance increases.
When we think about
adding on multiple
pressors in a shock
situation, you want to
think about vasopressin
in addition to
norepinephrine, especially
in septic shock.
Epinephrine is used
more in cardiac arrest,
as well as first line
for anaphylaxis. We're
going to see increases
in heart rate, systemic
vascular resistance,
and cardiac output.
For dopamine, there is
a few different agonisms
of the receptors, so
dopamine receptors, beta-1
receptors, alpha-1 receptors,
and beta-2 receptors.
Dopamine, typically not a
first line treatment. it
is a little bit of a messy
drug you can see with the
adverse effects here and
finally with dobutamine it's
only used for cardiogenic
shock it's an enotrope not
a vasopressor so mostly
beta-1 agonism and again
we'd expect to only see an
increase in cardiac output
and I'm bringing all these
things up with receptor
bindings not that I expect
you guys to focus in on this
slide of this entire
presentation because we had a
lot of information be
presented here but more as a
refresh of what you guys
have already learned and now
applying it to some
actual pathophysiology and
treatment so here are a few
slides on the summary of shock
this is from first aid
again the circle and the red
arrow is the primary
disturbance driving the shock
a few more slides discussing
the different types of shock
and now we have a few
questions to go over so
question one 18 year old
female presents to your office
severely fatigued reports
that she has had episodes
of diarrhea and vomiting
for the past four days
vitals are a temperature
of 1027 blood pressure
75 over 50 hurry 110
hemodynamic measurement reveals
an increased systemic
vascular resistance which
of the following is the
most likely diagnosis so
things to keep in mind
here we want to look at our
symptoms so diarrhea and
vomiting past four days
temperature okay they're
probably in some form of
shock right heart rate
is elevated to reflexive
tachycardia we have an
increase in SVR so I can
immediately rule out a
distributive shock, right?
Distributive shock is a drop
in SVR, not an increase.
So of these three, which
one can I think it is?
It is going to be
hypovolemic shock. So our
rationale here, diarrhea
and vomiting, the patient
is unable to retain or
replenish her fluids.
Elevated temperature,
think about this, in a
septic shock and hypovolemic
due to illness. Since
SVR is elevated, this
cannot be septic shock.
So really the only
other kind of reasonable
explanation for
these symptoms and
what's going on is
a hypoflammic shock.
Question 2. 85-year
-old man presents to the
emergency department with
fatigue his past medical
history of heart failure,
hypertension, and gout.
History reveals non
-adherence of medications
due to difficulty picking
up his prescriptions.
Vitals are temperature
of 98, blood pressure 74
over 41, heart rate 127,
respiratory rate 23.
Drugular veins are
distended. Which of
the following heatodynamic
measures do you
expect to find on
further examination?
Okay, so it could be a
lot going on here. So
we expect that he has heart
failure, hypertension,
doubt. He has jugular
veins distension.
So we want to immediately
start thinking about
a cardiogenic shock
here right he has the
history of heart failure
he has concerns with
hypertension he can't
pick up his medications so
let's start thinking
about cardiogenic shock
right off the bat d and
e gone right we know
cardiogenic shock has a
decrease in cardiac output
so now that that one's
done we can start
to eliminate a few
more options So, in
cardiogenic shock, we
would expect to see an
increase in systemic
vascular resistance.
So, B is out of play.
So, we now have two
final answers that we
can think about. Is it
going to be an increase
or decrease postcapillary
wedge pressure?
In an obstructive shock,
particularly a
pulmonary obstruction,
we would expect
to see a decrease
in postcapillary
wedge pressure.
However, in cardiogenic
shock, the insult
is happening with the
left ventricle. We
can't pump enough
fluid out of the heart.
So we would expect to see
an increase in postcapillary
wedge pressure, meaning
that A is our answer.
So this patient,
like we said, is in
cardiogenic shock. We
expect to see decreased
cardiac output, reflexive
vasoconstriction.
Postcapillary wedge
pressure is increased
as there's a backup
of fluid into the left
atrium due to left
ventricular failure.
Past medical history,
patient has a known history
of heart failure with non
-adherence to medications.
While obstructive shock
may appear similar, the
past medical history
points to heart failure.
So question three, 65
-year-old man brought
to the ED 30 minutes
after slicing his arm
while wood chopping,
leading to significant
blood loss, blood
pressure 92 over 58.
On examination, he
appears lethargic and
pale. His extremities
are cool to the touch.
which set of findings
would most likely represent
the body's physiologic
reaction within the
first 30 minutes of
patient's injury. So we want
to think here, hemorrhagic
or hypovolemic shock.
So we want to think
about what are the
qualities of our
hypovolemic shock.
Heart rate we would expect
to be increased, right,
because it's going to be
a reflexive tachycardia.
So that immediately
gets rid of A and B.
So total peripheral resistance,
this is not a distributive
shock situation, so we'd
want to expect an increase
in total peripheral
resistance, also known as SVR.
Finally, for cardiac
contractility, this is not
cardiogenic shock, right?
Our heart is able to pump
fine. The decreased
cardiac output is actually
due to a loss of stroke
volume, not the actual
musculature of the heart.
So, with all this being
said, we would expect E to
be our final answer. This
patient is in hypopholemic
shock. We would expect
to see a drop in blood
pressure with sympathetic
reflexive activation.
This causes increase in
heart rate and contractility,
not cardiac output.
Renin will be released in
an attempt to raise blood
pressure through the RAS
system. I know you guys may
have briefly talked about
renin, but even to answer this
question, you didn't really
need to know what renin
was. You could have used
the other three values here.
Question four. 75-year
-old nursing home resident
is brought to the emergency
department because
of confusion. He developed
a productive cost
with green sputum several
days ago. Temperature
is 102, pulse 110, blood
pressure 90 over 60.
Results of laboratory
studies show a white
blood cell count of
14,000, platelet count
of 50,000, and elevated
serum lactic acid.
Which set of
physiologic parameters
is most likely
for this patient?
So we want to read about
past medical history
and presenting illness,
HPI. Green sputum.
Okay, this could be
an infection. Elderly
individual, pulse is
elevated, white blood cell
count is through the
roof at 14,000. This
individual meets SERS
criteria as well as QSOFA.
So thinking about distributive
shock, what are our parameters?
So we want to think
about central venous
pressure is going
to be decreased.
So this can get rid of D and E.
Postcapillary wedge,
again these are
all decreased, it's
all running the same
way so we can't
eliminate anything.
Cardiac output, again
remember in distributive shock
that it's going to be
increased. So we can actually
get rid of C and A, and
systemic vascular resistance.
We honestly could
have started probably
here and eliminated
everything else.
In distributive shock, systemic
vascular resistance
is decreased.
So with that being
said, B is our answer.
Patient is in septic
shock. Primary disturbance
is a decrease in systemic
vascular resistance.
This causes an increase in
heart rate since we are not
losing fluid. we see an
increase in cardiac output.
Postcapillary wedge and
central venous pressure
will not increase.
Again, the hardest
functioning fine, the
issue is with vasodilation.
Question five, you're an
intern on call, page to see
39 year old male. He has past
medical history of cystic
fibrosis, had a bilateral
lung transplant two years
ago. He's taking a few
different immunosuppressants.
Vital signs are temp
of 102, blood pressure
70 over 35, heart rate
134, respirations 18.
What do you think
is the primary
disturbance causing
this patient's shock?
So the first question
we need to think about
is what's going on here?
He is mutasuppressed,
he has a history of
cystic fibrosis with
a lung transplant,
and now he has an
elevated fever, decreased
blood pressure, heart
rate is elevated,
respirations are 18.
So what are we thinking
here? What's the primary
disturbance? What type of
shock are we probably in?
By reading these
context clues, I
would probably assume
a septic shock.
So from that, we now need
to look at what's the
primary disturbance in
a septic or distributive
shock. It's a drop in
systemic vascular resistance.
Okay, perfect.
A, B, C,
all gone. Don't
care about them.
Now we go through
D, E, and F. All are
decreases in systemic
vascular resistance.
So we now need to
understand what type of
distributive shock.
Again, we said septic.
So E is actually our
explanation for an
anaphylactic shock. F is
due to neurogenic shock.
and then this C would be
a hypovolemic, B would
be due to an obstructive,
and A is actually
a cardiogenic. So that
leaves our answer of D.
This patient is in
septic shock, and the
primary disturbance
is a decrease in SVR.
Thank you very much for
listening to this lecture.
I hope it was enjoyable
and it all made sense.
And if you have a few minutes,
please fill out the survey.
I've done a few lectures
for you guys, but I
would really love to
continue to have feedback
so I can help improve
them in the future.
Keep on working hard
with your studies.
I know second year can
be extremely difficult.
You guys can all
do it and you'll
make it out to the other side.
Have a great day and
thank you so much.